<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="cosmic_voice_mode_v1">
  <copyright>
    Copyright © 2026 Playtron

    Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person obtaining a
    copy of this software and associated documentation files (the "Software"),
    to deal in the Software without restriction, including without limitation
    the rights to use, copy, modify, merge, publish, distribute, sublicense,
    and/or sell copies of the Software, and to permit persons to whom the
    Software is furnished to do so, subject to the following conditions:

    The above copyright notice and this permission notice (including the next
    paragraph) shall be included in all copies or substantial portions of the
    Software.

    THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS", WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EXPRESS OR
    IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO THE WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY,
    FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE AND NONINFRINGEMENT. IN NO EVENT SHALL
    THE AUTHORS OR COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, DAMAGES OR OTHER
    LIABILITY, WHETHER IN AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, TORT OR OTHERWISE, ARISING
    FROM, OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE SOFTWARE OR THE USE OR OTHER
    DEALINGS IN THE SOFTWARE.
  </copyright>

  <description summary="voice mode overlay and input protocol">
    This protocol allows clients to receive voice input events from the compositor.
    The compositor has full control over the voice mode orb overlay - clients
    only receive notifications and voice input events.
    
    Apps can register as voice input receivers:
    1. Window-specific: Receives events when that window is focused
    2. Default receiver: Receives events when no other receiver is focused
       (controlled by COSMIC_VOICE_DEFAULT_RECEIVER env var)
    
    When voice mode is activated via hotkey:
    - If a registered receiver window is focused, it gets start/stop/cancel
    - Otherwise, the default receiver (if any) gets the events
    
    The orb visual indicator shows where voice input is going:
    - Floating: Default receiver is handling voice input
    - Attached: A specific window is handling voice input
  </description>

  <interface name="zcosmic_voice_mode_manager_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="manager for voice mode">
      This interface allows clients to register as voice input receivers.
      The compositor controls voice mode; clients receive events.
    </description>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the manager">
        Destroy this manager object.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="register_receiver">
      <description summary="register as a voice input receiver">
        Register this client as a voice input receiver. The app_id identifies
        which windows can receive voice input when focused.
        
        If the app_id matches COSMIC_VOICE_DEFAULT_RECEIVER, this client
        becomes the default receiver for when no other receiver is focused.
      </description>
      <arg name="id" type="new_id" interface="zcosmic_voice_mode_v1"/>
      <arg name="app_id" type="string" summary="application ID"/>
    </request>
  </interface>

  <interface name="zcosmic_voice_mode_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="voice input receiver">
      This interface receives voice input events from the compositor.
      Events are sent based on focus and receiver registration.
    </description>

    <enum name="orb_state">
      <description summary="orb display states">
        The current display state of the orb.
      </description>
      <entry name="hidden" value="0" summary="orb is not visible"/>
      <entry name="floating" value="1" summary="orb is floating (default receiver active)"/>
      <entry name="attached" value="2" summary="orb is attached to a window"/>
    </enum>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="unregister as voice input receiver">
        Destroy this receiver and stop receiving voice input events.
      </description>
    </request>

    <event name="registered">
      <description summary="registration confirmed">
        Sent when registration is complete. Indicates whether this client
        is the default receiver or a window-specific receiver.
      </description>
      <arg name="is_default" type="uint" summary="1 if default receiver, 0 if window-specific"/>
    </event>

    <event name="start">
      <description summary="voice input started">
        Sent when voice input has started and this receiver should begin
        listening/recording. The client should start capturing audio.
      </description>
      <arg name="orb_state" type="uint" enum="orb_state" summary="where the orb is displayed"/>
    </event>

    <event name="stop">
      <description summary="voice input stopped">
        Sent when voice input has stopped normally (key released).
        The client should stop recording and process the audio.
      </description>
    </event>

    <event name="cancel">
      <description summary="voice input cancelled">
        Sent when voice input was cancelled (e.g., user switched focus,
        pressed escape, or another interruption). The client should
        discard any recorded audio.
      </description>
    </event>

    <event name="orb_attached">
      <description summary="orb attached to this receiver's window">
        Sent when the orb has visually attached to this receiver's window.
        Includes the window geometry for reference.
      </description>
      <arg name="x" type="int" summary="window x position"/>
      <arg name="y" type="int" summary="window y position"/>
      <arg name="width" type="int" summary="window width"/>
      <arg name="height" type="int" summary="window height"/>
    </event>

    <event name="orb_detached">
      <description summary="orb detached from this receiver's window">
        Sent when the orb has detached from this receiver's window
        (e.g., focus changed to another receiver or default).
      </description>
    </event>
  </interface>
</protocol>
